Guide to the Ralph W. Tyler Papers 1932-1988
University of Chicago Library
- Series IV: Writings by Tyler
  - Subseries 7: Speeches and Writings File
    - 1984/85, "Changing Concepts of Educational Evaluation." Chapter drafts for International Journal of Educational Research; Chapter 1, Societal Changes Influencing Educational Evaluation Chapter 2, The Old Paradigm and Its Shortcomings Chapter 3, Another Paradigm and a Rationale Chapter 4, Assessing Educational Potential Chapter 5, Program Evaluation Chapter 6, Evaluating the Written Compositions of Students Chapter 7, Evaluation of Affective Learning Chapter 8, Assessing the Educational Achievements of Large Populations Chapter 9, Evaluation in Human Resource Development Chapter 10, Reporting Results of Educational Evaluations (Box 74, Folder 4)
    - 1984/85/86, "Changing Concepts of Educational Evaluation." Typesetting corrections (Box 74, Folder 5)
    - 1985, "Charles Hubbard Judd; As I Came to Know Him." Article for Teaching Education (draft) "Developing Tests to Assist in the Improvement of Education." [Paper prepared for a proposed book by D. Wiley and R. Snow] (draft) Foreword to proposed Allison Davis Symposium volume (draft) Foreword to A History of Blackburn College, by G. McConaghall (draft) "Marginality in Schools." Foreword to Reaching Marginal Students (draft) (Box 74, Folder 6)
    - 1986, "The `Educator's Educator' Talks About Religious Education; An Interview with Ralph W. Tyler," by L. Townsend (2 transcript drafts) "Evaluation for Utilization." Passages from "Changing Concepts of Educational Evaluation" to be reprinted in an international handbook (galley proof) + 4 related items "Examining the Current Demands for Curriculum Reform from an Historical Perspective." Article for National Forum (draft) "The Five Most Significant Curriculum Events in the 20th Century." Presentation, ASCD headquarters building dedication, Alexandria, Va. (Box 74, Folder 7)
    - 1986, "The John Dewey Society's Early Activities as I Recall Them" (draft) + 1 related item "National Assessment of Educational Progress." Article for Encyclopedia of School Administration and Supervision (draft) "The Role of the Principal in Promoting Student Learning." First lecture, Ralph Tyler Distinguished Lecture Series, Joint Spring Conference, Massachusetts School Administrators (original and condensed drafts) "Voices for Curriculum Quality; Our Heritage in Social Education." Second Annual Louisiana Curriculum Conference, Baton Rouge (draft) + 1 related item (Box 74, Folder 8)
    - 1987, Foreword to a compendium of readings on qualitative evaluation, complied by J. Stone (draft) Introduction to Secondary Education, by J. Levine (draft) "Letters." Critique of Social Issues and Education, ASCD (draft) "Major Trends in Curriculum Research and Their Impacts on School Reform." Symposium paper, AERA Annual Meeting, Washington, D.C. (draft) "Progress in Dealing with Curriculum Problems." Chapter for NSSE 87th Yearbook, Part 1 (draft) "Ralph W. Tyler's Response to Items for Book on Educational Leaders" (ms. photocopy) + 2 related items "The Role of Public Schools in a Democratic Society." Conference of the University of Massachusetts Consortium for School Improvement (draft) "Utilization of Research by Practitioners in Education." Presented at the dedication of the Benton Center for Curriculum and Instruction, University of Chicago (draft) + 1 related item "What We Know About Learning and How That Influences Curriculum Renewal." Chapter for Massachusetts Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development Yearbook (draft) (Box 74, Folder 9)
    - Undated, "Accountability for What? To Whom?" (handwritten outline) "Achievement Testing and Instruction; A Discussion for Guidance and Personnel Workers" (fragment) "The Educational Potentials of 4-H" "Notes on RWT Speech to Trustees" [University of Chicago] "The Role of Education in World Development" (handwritten outline) "What Is the Responsibility of the School in the Development of Values?" (Box 74, Folder 10)
    - 1943-1955, Outlines, Fold-overs and cards. (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - 1956-1968, Outlines, Fold-overs and cards. (Box 75, Folder 2)
    - 1970-1975, Outlines, Fold-overs and cards. (Box 75, Folder 3)
    - 1976-1984, Outlines, Fold-overs and cards. 10 items (Box 75, Folder 4)
    - Undated, Outlines, Fold-overs and cards. (Box 75, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 8: Center for Advanced Study of the Behavioral Sciences
    - "Education-For What?" The Action People - A Provocative Series, Series I Volume IV, The Stone-Brandel Center, 1968, transcript, "Utilization of Educational Technology," n.d., carbon copy; "Achievement Testing and the Publisher; Opportunities and Options," n.d., typed; "Review of Experience and Research with Special Programs to Reach New Groups of Students," n.d., holograph draft (Box 75, Folder 6)
    - "The Autonomous Teacher," April 8, 1970, typed, presented at the Symposium on the Continuing Education of the Teacher, Palo Alto, CA; "New Concepts in Education and Learning Theory," n.d., carbon copy; "Experience in Related Fields; Parallels and Differences," n.d., typeset reprint (Box 75, Folder 7)
    - "Innovations in Our Schools and Colleges," July 21, 1965, typed, for the White House Conference on Education; "In-Service Training; Problems and Needs," December 2, 1963, carbon copy, for the Omaha Conference on Planning In-Service Training Programs; "American Needs the Experimental College," June 1963, offprint for the Antioch College commencement; "The Role of the Principal in Promoting Student Learning," n.d., typed (Box 75, Folder 8)
    - "Role of Assessment Information in Improving Education Programs," April 9, 1980, typed, for the American Educational Research Association; "Educational Evaluation; A Retrospective View, September 1, 1980, typed photocopy, for the American Psychological Association; "How We Got Where We Are," August 13, 1980, typed, for the University of California-Berkeley; "General Statement on Program Evaluation," n.d., typed draft (Box 75, Folder 9)
    - "Changing Horizons in Nursing Education," n.d., typed; "Meeting the Challenge of the Gifted," n.d., typed; "The Contribution of the Behavioral Sciences to Educational Research," n.d., typed, for the University of Virginia's Division of Educational Research; "What Insights and Research in Related Fields Have Relevance for the Identification, Analysis, and Solution of Basic Problems of Faculty-Administration Relations," n.d., typed (Box 75, Folder 10)
    - "Can A University Determine its Future?," March 11, 1973, typed, for the Higher Education Colloquium (Box 75, Folder 11)
    - "Developing Curriculum for Human Potential," n.d., typed; "If not I.Q.-What?," September 18, 1980, typed; "A Place Called School," n.d., holograph; "What Is Effectiveness and How Do We Bring It About?," December 9, 1979, typed (Box 75, Folder 12)
    - "Research on the Politics of Institutional Accreditation," March 28, 1977, typed (Box 75, Folder 13)
    - "An Advanced Study Center for Vocational Education; Goals and Challenges," October 31, 1978, typed, for the National Faculty Plenary Conference, Columbus, Ohio (Box 75, Folder 14)
    - "The Role of Standard Tests in Evaluating the Elementary School Program," March 2, 1959, carbon copy, for the Annual Meeting of Elementary School Principals, Los Angeles, CA (Box 75, Folder 15)
    - "The Use of Concepts in Developing A Curriculum," n.d., typed (Box 75, Folder 16)
    - "The Future of the University; Static and Change," March 8, 1973, typed, for the University of Kentucky (Box 75, Folder 17)
    - "Educating Supervisors for School in a Democratic Society," n.d., typed (Box 75, Folder 18)
    - "Improving the Educational Program," August 10-17, 1957, typed copy, fastened, prepared for the Milligan Workshop of the Council for the Advancement of Small Colleges, Milligan College, TN (Box 75, Folder 19)
    - "The Needs of Elementary and Secondary Education for the 1980s," n.d., typed copy; comments on "Practicals" (Box 76, Folder 1)
    - "The Tasks of UCEA for the ‘80s" (Box 76, Folder 2)
    - "Conducting Classes to Optimize Learning," n.d., typed; "Evaluation; The Ultimate Reality," August 9, 1966, typed, for the American Management Association, International Conference and Exhibit, New York (Box 76, Folder 3)
    - "Equity As a Priority for Education in a Democratic Society," n.d., holograph; "Education and Human Potential," February 16, 1981, typed, for the AASA conference; "Tasks for the UCEA for the '80s," June 22, 1983, typed, for the University Council for Educational Administration (Box 76, Folder 4)
    - "Strategies for Educational Leadership," April 1, 1969, typed, for the Conference of California Elementary School Administrators (Box 76, Folder 5)
    - "The Problems and Possibilities of Educational Evaluation," n.d., typed and photocopy, for the CED Supplementary Paper (Box 76, Folder 6)
    - "The Future and Implications for Education," April 3, 1977, typed, transcript of a lecture given at the Annual Conference of School Administrators, San Francisco, CA; "Review of Experience and Research with Special Programs to Reach New Groups of Students," June 26, 1980, typed, for the Educational Leaders conference, Los Angeles, CA; "Testing and the Publisher; Opportunities and Options," March 14, 1980, typed; "The Future of Teacher Education," April 30, 1976, typed, for the Fitchburg Conference (Box 76, Folder 7)
    - "Developing Tests to Assist in the Improvement of Education," n.d., typed; "What is an Ideal Program?," July 29, 1968, typed, for the Bureau of Reference Services, State Department of Education, Sacramento, CA; "Panel on Testing and Evaluation," July 15, 1981, holograph, for Superintendent's Conference, Teachers College, Columbia University, NY, NY; "Evaluation of General Extension in Land-Grant Institutions," Nov. 12, 1961, photocopy of offprint, for the 75th Annual Convention of the American Association of Land-Grant Colleges and State Universities, Kansas City, MO (Box 76, Folder 8)
    - "Schooling and Society," 1981, offprint, for the Perry Dunlap Smith Memorial Lecture Series, Roosevelt University Chicago, IL; "The Teacher and the Philosophy of Education in the Chicago Public Schools," January 16, 1950, typed carbon copy; "The Values of Cooperative Education from a Pedagogical Perspective," April 23, 1981, typed draft, for the Second World Conference on Cooperative Education (Box 76, Folder 9)
    - "Effective Teaching; Neglected Practices from the Past," October 25, 1979, typed, for the National Symposium on Improving Instruction, University of Illinois, Urbana, IL (Box 76, Folder 10)
    - "Dewey's Impact on Modern Education," November 14, 1967, typed, for the Annual John Dewey Lecture, University of Chicago Laboratory Schools, Chicago, IL (Box 76, Folder 11)
    - "School-Centered Educational Reform," October 18, 1978, typed, for the National Symposium on Targets for School Improvement, University of Illinois, Urbana, IL; "Historical Trends in Large-Scale Assessment," April 25, 1984, typed, for the National Council on Measurement in Education, New Orleans, LA (Box 76, Folder 12)
    - "Changing Responsibilities of Higher Education," October 3, 1969, typed carbon, for the Pennsylvania Library Association, Pittsburgh, PA; "Horizons in Nursing," October 26, 1963, typed, for the Inaugural Forum, College of Nursing, Marquette University, Milwaukee, WI (Box 76, Folder 13)
    - "Educational Measurement; Where We Have Been, Where We Are Now, and Where We Are Going," 1985, University of Texas, San Antonio, TX (Box 76, Folder 14)
    - "Method, Motivation, and Mystique in Learning," October 1977, typed, for the National Symposium on Teaching and Learning, sponsored by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Chicago, IL (Box 76, Folder 15)
    - "Future Development of Continuing Education," n.d., typed; "America's Impact on Education Throughout the World," June 16, 1976, Bicentennial Lecture, University of Minnesota; "Importance and Nature of Educational Leadership," August 19, 1982, holograph notes; "Establishing Guidelines for Industrial Arts in Career Education; A Keynote Statement," n.d.; "School Discipline; License or Suppression?," ca. 1941, typed outline notes; "Educational Assessment Standards and Quality; Can We Have One Without the Others?," June 7, 1982, holograph notes, for the Conference on Large-Scale Assessment, Boulder, CO; "Unique Mission of Our Public Schools," August 31, 1982, holograph notes, for the Evanston Institute; "A State Strategy for Evaluating Educational Progress," October 1, 1968, photocopied holograph notes, for the PNAC-Conference on Innovation, Title III ESFA (Box 76, Folder 16)
    - "American Education in the Perspective of Education in Other Nations," n.d., typed; "What Have We Learned About Learning? An Overview," July 30, 1976, typed, for the Chief State School Officers, Summer Institute; "Teacher Education and the Improvement of Instruction," August 10, 1979, for the International Council on Education for Teaching, Seoul, Korea (Box 76, Folder 17)
    - "Shaping the Future of American Higher Education; Lessons from the 1930s," n.d., typed and holograph draft; "Developing A Philosophy of Education for the Gary Schools," August 1945; "Educability and the Schools," n.d., typed copy (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - "Institutional Organization of the Behavioral Sciences," n.d., offprint, Voice of America, Forum Lecture Series; "The Values of Cooperative Education," December 6, 1960, offprint, for the Founder's Day Convocation, Drexel Institute of Technology; "Do We Need a `National Curriculum'?," January 1959, offprint, for the Conference on Policies and Strategy for Strengthening Curriculum of the American Public Schools, Stanford, CA; "The Knowledge Explosion; Implications for Secondary Education," October 1964, offprint, for the Illinois Association of Secondary School Principals, University of Illinois; "Function of the Graduate School in the Education of Teachers," October 29, 1942, photocopy of conference notes, Annual Convention of Association of Land-Grant Colleges and Universities Chicago, IL. (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - "Neglected Areas of Basic Research in the Social Sciences," December 30, 1954, typed (missing pages 3-5, 7-8), for the Berkeley Meeting of the Industrial Science Section, American Association for the Advancement of Science; "The Rainbow of Promise," n.d., photocopy of typed ms., Doane College Commencement Address, Crete, NE; "Needed Research on the Education of Older Adults," n.d., typed (Box 77, Folder 3)
    - Offprints of articles written by RWT, "Trends in Teaching; How Research is Affecting Our Understanding of the Learning Process," The School Review, May 1951 "Meeting the Challenge of the Gifted," The Elementary School Journal, November 1957 "Needed Research in the Field of Tests and Examinations," Educational Research Bulletin, September 1936 "Appraisal of Military Training and Experience," Journal of the American Association of Collegiate Registrars," July 1943 "Placement Tests as a Means of Determining Advanced Standing at the University of Chicago," Journal of the American Association of Collegiate Registrars, July 1945 "Next Steps in Improving Secondary Education," The School Review, December 1952 "Clarifying the Role of the Elementary School," The Elementary School Journal, November 1956 "Trends in Teaching; How Research Is Affecting Our Understanding of the Learning Process," The School Review, May 1951 "Education; Balancing Conditioned Response and Responsible Claims," Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences, June 1971 "The Curriculum, Then and Now," The Elementary School Journal, April 1957 "The Distinctive Attributes of Education for the Professions," Social Work Journal, April 1952 "Some Guiding Principles for Decision-Making," Measurement and Research in Today's Schools, 1961 "Educational Objectives of American Democracy," The Nation's Children, Vol. II; Development and Education, 1960 "The Integration of Educational Experiences," National Society for the Study of Education, Yearbook, 1958 (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript chapters, including, "The Use of Expectancy Scores Is Misleading," typed "The Minimum Competency Movement...," holograph, copy "Educational Objectives and Educational Testing; Problems Now Faced," typed "The Curriculum," typed draft (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - Manuscripts, including, "A Place Called School," typed draft, n.d. "The Five Most Significant Curriculum Events in the Twentieth Century," holograph "Affective Issues in the School Curriculum," typed and holograph copies "Comparing the Use of Research in Other Professions with Research in Education," chapter 2 of ASCD Yearbook, gallery copy "Curriculum Development and Research," chapter 3 of ASCD Yearbook, galley copy "Guide to Educational Troubleshooting," typed draft (Box 77, Folder 6)
    - Article manuscript, "Attaining Quality Education," (1986) (Box 77, Folder 7)
    - "National Assessment of Educational Progress," article draft, typed, Correspondence related to publication "The Form of Objectives," galleys Introduction and one chapter of Learning in School and College, typed carbon copy, correspondence relating to the ms. (Box 77, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous manuscript drafts, typed; photocopy of "An Overview of Basic Principles of Curriculum and Instruction," 1961 (Box 77, Folder 9)
    - Manuscript drafts and correspondence with editors, especially Dorothy Neubauer, related to the text, Basic Principles of Curriculum (Box 77, Folder 10)
    - Manuscript chapters, drafts, including "What We Know About Learning and How That Influences Curriculum Renewal," chapter one from Renewing School Curriculum; Concerns for Equal and Quality Education (Box 77, Folder 11)
    - Manuscript drafts, Introduction to Forced to the Margins, entitled "Marginality in Schools" "Seventy-Five Years of Excellence in Education; Continuing the Quest," for the Education Forum "Attaining Quality Education," for American Middle School Education "Conditioning and Self-Directed Learning in Education" "International Encyclopedia of Education, Article in Curriculum Resources," working draft "What We've Learned from Past Studies of Teacher Education" (Box 77, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 9: Publications
    - Basic Principles of Curriculum, full typed draft, with corrections (Box 78, Folder 1)
    - Copies of publications and oversized off-prints., "Achievement Testing and Curriculum Construction," Board of Examiners, The University of Chicago, n.d. "Assessing Educational Achievement in the Affective Domain, NCME, Spring 1973 "Education in a World of Change," Journal of Home Economics, September 1962 "The Interrelationship of Knowledge," Professional Reprints in Education, February 1964 "Implications of Behavioral Studies for Health Education," The Journal of School Health, January 1963 Report on Cooperative Education; Summary of the National Study, RWT and Annice L. Mills, New York, 1961 "Behavioral Science Goes to College," Contemporary Psychology, November 1962 "What the Assessment of Education Will Ask," Nation's Schools, November 1966 "How Can Engineering Education Increase Student Learning?" Engineering Education, September 1966 "The Contribution of `A Study of Schooling' to Educational Research," Educational Leadership, April 1983 "Emphasize Tasks Appropriate for the School," Phi Delta Kappa, November 1958 "Curriculum Development Since 1900," ASCD, n.d., galley copy (Box 78, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous professional articles collected by RWT relating to education, curriculum, and youth (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified notes, typed and holograph (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified notes, typed and holograph (Box 78, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified notes, typed and holograph (Box 78, Folder 6)
    - Photocopies of brochure for "Conference on Examinations," held September 16-19, 1939, Dinard, France. Materials related to Charles Hubbard Judd (1873-1946), saved by RWT (Box 78, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 10: Academic and Professional Material
    - Professional conference and seminar materials, papers, and miscellany (Box 78, Folder 8)
    - Class materials, EDA-384G, Fall 1980 (Box 78, Folder 9)
    - Conference material, Study Group on National Assessment (Box 79, Folder 1)
    - Material related to teaching at Hebrew University of Jerusalem (Box 79, Folder 2)
    - Class materials for curriculum seminar (Box 79, Folder 3)
    - Material related to teaching at the Center for Curriculum Studies, University of Massachusetts (Box 79, Folder 4)
    - Transcripts of RWT lectures (Box 79, Folder 5)
    - Transcripts of RWT lectures (Box 79, Folder 6)
    - The Leadership Academy Workshop, "Evaluating Program Success," by RWT, December 25, 1984, Haywood, CA (Box 79, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 11: Speeches, 1982-1983
    - Speeches and papers, May-December 1982, "The Tasks of UCEA for the ‘80s." (2 copies) "Seminar on Attaining Quality Education." (2 copies) "Sidney Leavitt Pressey, 1888-1979, A Biographical Memoir." (1 draft and 2 copies) (Box 79, Folder 8)
    - Speeches and papers, May-December 1982, "Curriculum Development and Research" "The Use of Research by Engineers" (Box 79, Folder 9)
    - Speeches and papers, May-December 1982, Letter and drafts (Box 79, Folder 10)
    - Speeches and papers, May-December 1982, "Comment by Ralph W. Tyler." (1 copy, 1 draft) "International Encyclopedia of Educational Research." "The Eight Year Study." (Box 79, Folder 11)
    - Speeches and papers, May-December 1982, "Educational Assessment; Standards and Quality: Can We Have One Without the Other?" (2 copies, 1 draft) (Box 79, Folder 12)
    - Speeches and papers, January-July 1983, "A Study of Schooling: Its Contributions to Educational Research and the Understanding of Schools." (1 draft, 3 copies) (Box 79, Folder 13)
    - January 1983 (Box 79, Folder 14)
    - March 1983 (Box 80, Folder 1)
    - May 1983 (Box 80, Folder 2)
    - June 1983 (Box 80, Folder 3)
    - August- September 1983 (Box 80, Folder 4)
    - "Affective Issues in the School Curriculum." (3 copies) (Box 80, Folder 5)
    - "Conditions for Effective Learning." (1 draft and 3 copies) (Box 80, Folder 6)
    - "Educating Children and Youth for Lives of Freedom Synopsis." (1 draft, 3 copies) "Educating Supervisors for School in a Democratic Society." (Box 80, Folder 7)
    - "Using Technology to Improve Education." (1 draft, 3 copies) (Box 80, Folder 8)
    - Curriculum vitae (Box 80, Folder 9)
    - "Beyond 1984: Education for Freedom, Strength and Peace." (1 draft, 3 copies) (Box 80, Folder 10)
    - Undated, 1980s (?), "The John Dewey Society’s Early Activities as I Recall Them." "National Assessment of Educational Progress." "The Role of the Principal in Promoting Student Learning." "Stimulations for Reform." "Introduction to Secondary Instruction: A Handbook for the Classroom Teacher." "Letters." Untitled. (Box 80, Folder 11)
    - Undated, 1980s (?), "Progress in Dealing with Curriculum Problems." "What We Know About Learning and How That Influences Curriculum Renewal." "Examining the Current Demands for Curriculum Reforms from an Historical Perspective." Untitled. "Supervision as a Profession." "The Governance of the National Assessment of Educational Reform." "Historical Trends in Large-Scale Assessment." (Box 80, Folder 12)
    - Items Related, "Major Trends in Curriculum Research and the Impacts on School Reform." (title page only) "Educational Reforms." (title page only) "What We Know About Learning and How That Influences Curriculum Renewal." (title page only) Various government publication excerpts 2 cover letters, dated 1986 "Preface to Harold Dunkel’s Writ in Water." (Box 80, Folder 13)
- Series V: Writings by Others
  - Subseries 1: Reports
    - "If Not I.Q. - What?" September 18, 1980 (Box 80, Folder 14)